Loyalty without question. Friendship without equal.
Mrs Brown is a drama, history, romance film directed by John Madden.
When Queen Victoria's husband Prince Albert dies, she
finds solace in her trusted servant, Mr.
John Brown.
But their relationship also brings scandal and turmoil to the monarchy.
Queen Victoria, played by Judi Dench.
John Brown, played by Billy Connolly.
Henry Ponsonby, played by Geoffrey Palmer.
Prime Minister Benjamin Disraeli, played by Antony Sher.
Archie Brown, played by Gerard Butler.
Doctor Jenner, played by Richard Pasco.
Mrs Brown (also released in cinemas as Her Majesty, Mrs Brown) is a 1997 British drama film starring Judi
Dench, Billy Connolly, Geoffrey Palmer, Antony Sher, and Gerard Butler in his film debut.
It was written by Jeremy Brock and directed by John Madden.
The film was produced by the BBC and Ecosse Films with the intention of
being shown on BBC One and on WGBH's Masterpiece Theatre.
However, it was acquired by Miramax and released to unexpected
success, going on to earn more than $13.2 million worldwide.
The story concerns a recently widowed Queen Victoria and her relationship with a Scottish servant, John
Brown, a trusted servant of her deceased husband, and the subsequent uproar it provoked.
Brown had served Victoria's Prince Consort, Prince Albert; Victoria's Household thought Brown might
help the Queen who had remained in mourning since the Prince Consort's death in 1861.
The film was screened in the Un Certain Regard section at the 1997 Cannes Film
Festival and released in the United Kingdom on 5 September 1997.
Judi Dench won the Golden Globe Award for Best Actress in a Motion Picture – Drama and the BAFTA Award for Best Actress in a Leading Role; additionally, she was nominated for many other awards for her performance, including
the Academy Award for Best Actress and the Screen Actors Guild Award for Outstanding Performance by a Female Actor in a Leading Role, but lost both awards to Helen Hunt for her role in As Good as It Gets.
The film explores themes of assassination, england, scotland, widow, queen.
The tone is emotional.